understood all the different types of returns that you can see in and around mutual funds.
Let us try and understand the two kind of risks that you will see in the mutual funds space.
So there are two risks that we will try and understand now. First is beta, another is standard deviation.
So we will not only try and understand what this actually means, but the objective also is to try and
understand how do you how do you interpret each of that data right. So let us start with standard deviation
first. So now say for example you go to a client, the client the typical first question that
the client asks you is how much return will this investment give you correct.
On what basis do you or me go and tell them what is the return expectation. So what you
and I do is go back you get the last three or five year data and tell the client that if the fund
in the last three year has given 12% return, you can theoretically expect the fund to continue to give
you 12% return. That is how you and I said expectation with the client looking at the past returns
and helping the client understand that if in the past fund gave 12% expect 12% returns from the fund.
But tell me one thing if the fund in the past has given 12% what is the assurability that fund in
the future will continue to give 12% I am sure you will concur that there is no such assurability is
exactly where standard deviation comes into picture or what is standard deviation. So let us say I look
at the last three year returns average which is also called as me you call it average whatever you
want. So I look at the last three years average and I see that the last three years average is 12%
I tell the client look last three years the fund has given 12% expect 12% returns from the fund
but you and I both know that it is not necessary that the fund will generate 12% returns right.
It can generate higher in good situations it can generate worst in bad situation. Now the client wants
to know that if 12% is a fair expectation what is the range in which the returns can actually generate
given looking at the past data is where you look at something called as standard deviation.
Okay let me just write SD let's say SD of the fund is 15 what does this mean this means that
though you are expecting the fund to give you 12% return fund can give you higher in good situation
higher how much higher how much is given as mean plus standard deviation. So I am saying the fund
will average give me 12% but in good times there can be a deviation of 15 and hence it can give me
27% in good times in bad times how much can the fund give you. So I am saying I am expecting
average but in bad times it might give me less minus standard deviation. So in bad times it can give me
12 minus 15 minus 3% what is standard deviation it says that if your last three years average return
expectation is 12 or last three years returns that have got generated at 12% and you are expecting 12%
to continue you might not get 12% you might be able to figure out the range if the standard deviation
is 15 the range of this though your expectation is 12% your fund can generate returns anywhere between
27% on the higher side to minus 3% on the lower side. So the way it works is very simple you look at
the last three years data you tell the client client loop in the last three years it has given 12%
so I am assuming it will give 12% but I am not sure if it can give exactly 12% but I can give you
a range the fund can range between my plus 27% returns on the higher side and minus 3% return on
the lower side that is what is standard deviation and that is how you use it. Why do you call standard
deviation a risk let's say for example in the same case of 12% as mean I am saying this fund
has a standard deviation of 20 what does this mean that you will expect 12% return from the fund but the
range can be what 12 plus 20 32% on the higher side you are very happy as long as you are making more
you are happy but on the lower side the range can be 12 minus 20 minus 8% so now we are telling the
client that look in the standard deviation is 20 the range is going to be 32% on the higher side to
minus 8% on the lower side I am sure you will agree higher the range higher the risk is because higher
is going to be the volatility right so if I am expecting in very simple terms if I am expecting
in case 1 12% my returns can vary on the higher side 27 and on the lower side minus 3 so
the fluctuations can be this in returns but as soon as the range increases and becomes minus 8
the volatility of the fund increases and hence we call this as a risk so higher the standard deviation
higher is the risk in the fund right so let's say for example if there are fund if there are two
funds fund a fund b and both have generated 12% return hypothetically and we are saying this fund as
a standard deviation of 15 and this as a standard deviation of 13 then probably this fund is a better
bit right is because it could generate the same return by taking lower risk but you just don't look at
this data we will compile everything that we are learning in risk and return together at the end
but I am just trying to help you understand each of these concepts one by one I hope you
understood why standard deviation is a risk and why higher the standard deviation higher the range
and hence higher the risk I hope standard deviation is absolutely clear let's try and understand
what is beta so beta is also a risk what does this mean beta is actually called as the market risk
and I forgot to mention standard deviation is called as the portfolio risk right now talking
about beta beta market risk is because I am going to compare beta with the so the risk of the portfolio
with the risk of the market hence it is called market risk in standard deviation I am comparing of
the I am only comparing the risk of the portfolio I am not talking about its relationship with the market
so standard deviation is called portfolio risk and beta is called market risk because I am talking
about the risk of the portfolio with respect to the market now beta of the index is always given as one
this is an assumption this is with this entire theory is made now if I say that the beta of reliance
industries stock is also one what I am trying to say is that the risk of the index and the risk of reliance
is almost the same which also means that the return should almost be the same which is why you say
if the market goes at 10% you are expecting reliance also to generate 10% returns if the market falls
5% you are expecting reliance also to fall 5% if the market gives minus 2% you expect reliance also
to give minus 2% but if I say that the beta of reliance stock is 0.5 which means I am taking risk
which is half of that of the index so my returns are also going to be half of that of the index
say the index goes up 10% I am expected to go up 5% if the index falls minus 5% I am expected to fall
half minus 2.5% if the index falls minus 2% I am expected to fall half which is why my risk
because my risk is half my return also expected is half suppose if the beta of reliance
is 2 which means if index is 1 I am taking twice as much as risk which means my return expectation is
also going to be twice as much as index so index is 10% I will be expected to generate 20%
if index fell 5% I will fall 10% if index falls 2% I am expected to fall 4%
1 beta is called neutral in the market less than 1 is called low beta or you also call them as
defensive stocks more than 1 you call them high beta or you call them aggressive stocks
right so beta is the market risk because I am helping understand how much will my stock move
versus the index and hence we calling the market risk standard deviation we are not concerned
of where the market moves I am only talking about the risk of my portfolio and standard deviation is
called the portfolio risk now you understood why higher the beta is a risk because I am hoping when
okay when the market goes up I will go up fair enough but when the market falls I fall more and hence
we call higher the beta higher risky same example that I gave you which standard deviation I will repeat
let's say fund A generates 12% fund B also generates 12% but beta fund A was 1 and beta of fund B
was 0.5 then I will say fund B is done well because with taking lower risk they will be able to
generate the same return again like I told you in standard deviation you and me will not compare
funds like this just looking at the standard deviation or just looking at the beta or just looking at
rolling returns we are going to use all of that in conjunction to figure out the fund all I am trying
to do right now is helping you understand each of these concepts so that we can use it to select the fund
in a bit I hope you understood thank you so much